A Finding Aid to the Jan Butterfield Papers, 1950-1997, in the Archives of American Art AAA.buttjan
Archives of American Art
- Printed Materials, 1961-1997; Series 5; 1.8 Linear feet Boxes 11-12, 16, OV 17-19
  - Publicity (Box 12)
    - "Helter Skelter" Exhibition (1992), Museum of Contemporary Art (Box 12, Folder 28)
      Oversized materials moved to Box 16, folder 5.
    - Maricia Gygli King, 1988-1990 (Box 12, Folder 29)
    - Los Angeles County Museum of Art, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 30)
    - Museum of Art and History (Santa Cruz, Calif.), 1997 (Box 12, Folder 31)
    - Bruce Nauman, 1994 (Box 12, Folder 32)
    - Gount Giuseppe Panza di Biumo Gift to the Museum of Contemporary Art, 1994 (Box 12, Folder 33)
    - Victor Raphael, 1989-1995 (Box 12, Folder 34)
    - Miscellaneous, 1993-1994 (Box 12, Folder 35)
  - Readings for "Issues in Contemporary Art", circa 1975 (Box 12, Folder 36-40)
  - Scrapbook, "Ed Kienholz" (1966), Los Angeles County Museum of Art (Box 12, Folder 41)
  - Special Publications (Box 12)
    - Artists' Soapbox Derby Official Magazine, 1975, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 42)
    - The Jounal of Art, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 43)
      Oversized material moved to Box 16, folder 6.
    - "Los Angeles County Art Museum," Los Angeles Times Supplement, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 44)
    - Looking Critically: 21 Years of ArtForum Magazine, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 45)
    - Museum of California, 1982 (Box 12, Folder 46)
    - The New Art Space, Los Angeles Institute of Contemporary Art, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 47)
  - Oversized Articles by Butterfield, Craig Kaufman (Box 16, Folder 3)
    Oversized material from Box 11, folder 36.
  - Oversized Articles by Butterfield, Tony Labat (Box 16, Folder 3)
    Oversized material from Box 11, folder 37.
  - Oversized Article by Henry Hopkins, "West Coast Style" (Box 16, Folder 3)
    Oversized material from Box 11, folder 48.
  - Oversized Article about Butterfield, Art of Light and Space Review (Box 16, Folder 3)
    Oversized material from Box 11, folder 49.
  - Oversized Clippings, Sam Francis (Box 16, Folder 4)
    Oversized materials from Box 11, folder 53.
  - Oversized Clippings, General, 1968-1975 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    Oversized materials from Box 11, folder 57.
  - Oversized Exhibition Catalogs, "The Human Condition," San Francisco Museum of Modern Art (Box 16, Folder 5)
    Oversized material from Box 11, folder 64.
  - Oversized Exhibition Catalogs, Sam Francis, 1979-1980 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    Oversized materials from Box 12, folder 3.
  - Oversized Exhibition Posters, Ferus Gallery (Box 16, Folder 5)
    Oversized material from Box 12, folder 17.
  - Oversized Publicity, "Helter Skelter" Exihbition, MOCA (Box 16, Folder 5)
    Oversized materials from Box 12, folder 28.
  - Oversized Special Publications, The Journal of Art (Box 16, Folder 6)
    Oversized material from Box 12, folder 43.
  - Oversized Special Publications, Museum of California (Box 16, Folder 6)
    Oversized materials from Box 12, folder 46.
  - Oversized Clippings, Henry Hopkins (Box 17)
    Oversized materials from Box 11, folder 54.
  - Oversized Clippings, General, 1990-1991 (Box 17)
    Oversized material from Box 11, folder 59.
  - Oversized Clippings, General, 1992-1993 (Box 18)
    Oversized material from Box 11, folder 60.
  - Oversized Clippings, General, 1994-1997 (Box 18)
    Oversized material from Box 11, folder 61.
  - Oversized Publicity, Richard Diebenkorn (Box 18)
    Oversized material from Box 12, folder 22.
  - Oversized Exhibition Posters, Robert Hudson, Moore College (Box 19)
    Oversized material from Box 12, folder 18.
  - Oversized Plans (Box 19)
    Oversized material from Box 12, folder 19.
- Photographs, 1958-1994; Series 6; 2.2 Linear feet Boxes 12-14, 16
  This series contains photographs of Butterfield's friends, associates, and family, her travels to China and Greece, and her wedding to Henry Hopkins. Photographs of people include artists Philip Guston, Ed Kienholz, Henry Hopkins with Clyfford Still, Robert Irwin, Robert Rauschenberg, and a group photograph for the Los Angeles Magazine feature, "LA Art in the 1960s," the published version of which is found in series 5, Printed Materials. The bulk of this series consists of photographs of works of art, arranged by artist, with a few photographs of exhibitions at the end of the series.
  Most of the photographs are either prints or slides, but some negatives and contact sheets are also found. Most are of unknown origin or were taken by others, except for the photographs of Philip Guston, and photographs of works of art by Michael Brewster, Ron Davis, Robert Irwin, and Ed Ruscha, which are credited Jan Butterfield.
  Additional photographs are found in series 2, Writings, and series 3, Project Files.
  - People (Box 12)
    - Philip Guston, photographs by Jan Butterfield, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 48)
    - Ed Kienholz, circa 1970 (Box 12, Folder 49)
    - Henry Hopkins with Clyfford Still, circa 1976 (Box 12, Folder 50)
    - Robert Irwin, 1979, undated (Box 12, Folder 51)
    - Group for "LA Art in the 1960s" Article, LA Magazine, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 52)
    - Robert Rauschenberg, circa 1970s (Box 12, Folder 53)
    - James Turrell, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 54)
  - Personal (Box 12)
    - Butterfield with Unidentified Others, circa 1980; Contact sheets (Box 12, Folder 55)
    - Wedding of Butterfield and Henry Hopkins, circa 1970; Contact sheets (Box 12, Folder 56)
    - China, circa 1980; Contact sheets, negatives, and slides (Box 12, Folder 57-58)
    - Greece, circa 1980s; Negatives and slides (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified, 1988, undated; Negatives and prints (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Works of Art (Box 13)
    - Michael Asher, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Larry Bell, 1972-1981 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Billy Al Bengston, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Fletcher Benton, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Michael Brewster, photographs by Jan Butterfield, 1981; Negatives and prints (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Michael Brewster, 1972-1979 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Joan Brown, 1974-1978 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Judy Chicago, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Ron Cooper, 1972-1973 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Mary Corse, 1967-1968 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Eric de la Cova, 1984-1988 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Leonard Cutrow, 1960-1988 (Box 13, Folder 14-17)
    - Ron Davis, photograph by Jan Butterfield, circa 1974-1975 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - Richard Diebenkorn, 1975, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - Guy Dill, 1970-1991 (Box 13, Folder 20-22)
    - Toni Dove, 1988-1989 (Box 13, Folder 23)
    - Tom Eatherton, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 24)
    - Jules Engel, undated (Box 13, Folder 25)
    - Peter Erskine, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 26)
    - Joe Fay, 1988-1990 (Box 13, Folder 27)
    - Lorser Feitelson, 1980, undated (Box 13, Folder 28)
    - Oskar Fischinger, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 29)
    - Roy Fowler, 1985-1988 (Box 13, Folder 30)
    - Hans Frabel, undated (Box 13, Folder 31)
    - Sam Francis, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 32)
    - David Furman, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 33)
    - Paul Georges, 1978-1988 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Philip Guston, circa 1979 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Helen and Newton Harrision, Installation View, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Robert Hudson, 1979-1988 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Malou Flato, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Robert Irwin (Box 14)
      - Photographs by Jan Butterfield, Negatives, contact sheets, and prints. (Box 14, Folder 6)
      - Slides and Transparencies, 1975-1992 (Box 14, Folder 7)
      - Prints, 1971-1985 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Dean Johnson, 1983-1989 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Eric Johnson, 1990-1994 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Marcia King, 1984-1989 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Peter Krasnow, 1976, undated (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Anne Labriola, circa 1991 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Rico Lebrun, undated (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Helen Lundberg, circa 1975, undated (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Mary Malott, 1986 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - John McLaughlin, 1977, undated (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Ed Moses, 1970 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Bruce Nauman, 1970-1973 (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Maria Nordman, 1973-1976 (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Eric Orr, 1983 (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - Helen Pashgian, undated (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Agnes Pelton, undated (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Edward Ruscha, photograph by Jan Butterfield, circa 1970 (Box 14, Folder 24)
    - Richard Shaw, 1987-1988 (Box 14, Folder 25)
    - Henriette Stone, undated (Box 14, Folder 26)
    - Inez Storer, 1987-1988 (Box 14, Folder 27)
    - Sarah Tamor, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 28)
    - Hap Tivey, circa 1974-1990 (Box 14, Folder 29-31)
    - James Turrell, 1967-1991 (Box 14, Folder 32)
    - Doug Wheeler, circa 1981 (Box 14, Folder 33)
    - DeWain Valentine, 1968-1989 (Box 14, Folder 34)
    - Susan Kaiser Vogel, 1977-1991 (Box 14, Folder 35)
      Oversized material moved to Box 16, folder 7.
    - Peter Voulkos, circa 1958 (Box 14, Folder 36)
    - Elyn Zimmerman, 1980-1981 (Box 14, Folder 37)
    - Artist Unidentified, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 14, Folder 38)
    - Exhibitions (Box 14)
      - "A Time and Place," (1991) Los Angeles County Museum of Art (Box 14, Folder 39)
      - "Expressionist Utopia," (1993), Los Angeles County Museum of Art, 1993-1994; Also contains press release. (Box 14, Folder 40)
      - Mary Miss and Roland Reiss, Mount Saint Mary's College, 1980 (Box 14, Folder 41)
  - Oversized Photographs, Works of Art, Susan Kaiser Vogel (Box 16, Folder 7)
    Oversized material from Box 14, folder 35.
- Sound and Video Recordings, 1987-1997; Series 7; 0.4 Linear feet Box 15
  This series contains 4 videocassettes (VHS) and 1 sound cassette with art-related recordings. Videos include The Painter Sam Francis (1992); Breathing Light (circa 1988), about a work of the same title by Peter Erskine; documentation of three multimedia installations by Judit Hersko including Zurbaran Bewitched, Witch-hunt, and Black Forest Requiem, and a documentation of performances and experiments with light entitled Light Dance by Seth Riskin (1987-1995). The sound cassette is an acoustiguide for the 1990 Edward Ruscha exhibition at the Los Angeles Museum of Contemporary Art. A single unlabeled cassette containing what appears to be a band rehearsal is also found.
  Most of the sound recordings in the collection are found in series 1, Interviews and Lectures. Additional audio recordings are found in series 3, Project Files. Additional video recordings are found in the Publicity subseries of series 2, Writings, and in the correspondence subseries of series 3, Personal Business Records.
  - Light Dance, 1987-1995; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Breathing Light, circa 1988; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - The Painter Sam Francis, 1992; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Judit Hersko Installations, circa 1997; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Edward Ruscha Acoustiguide, 1990; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Unidentified Musical Recording, undated; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 15, Folder 6)